Guide to the Robert O. Paxton papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Robert O. Paxton Papers
1968-2004
Paxton, Robert O.
3 linear ft. (6 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
5439898
MS#0983
Biographical Note
Robert Owen Paxton [B.A. (1954), Washington & Lee University; B.A. (1956) and M.A. (1961), Oxford University; Ph. D. (1963), Harvard University], was born June 15, 1932, in Lexington, Virginia. An esteemed historian and the award-winning author of numerous books including The Anatomy of Fascism (2004), Vichy France and the Jews (1981), and Vichy France: Old Guard and New Order, 1940-44 (1972), Paxton is professor emeritus at Columbia University, where he taught from 1969 to 1997. He read history at Oxford as a Rhodes Scholar from 1954 to 1956. His subsequent awards and honors include fellowships from the American Council of Learned Societies (1974-75) and the Rockefeller Foundation (1978-79), as well as designations as chevalier by the Ordre National des Arts et des Lettres and officier by the Ordre National du Merite (France).
Widely regarded as the premier scholar on the history of Vichy France, Paxton was the first historian to fully explore the circumstances and extent of France's collaboration with Nazi Germany during World War II. His work is particularly renowned in France. Elisabeth Bumiller wrote in The New York Times that Paxton is the “intellectual godfather to a new and influential generation of French historians.” A frequent contributor to The New York Review of Books and numerous other publications, Paxton taught at the University of California, Berkeley, and the State University of New York at Stony Brook before he joined the Columbia faculty.
Scope and Content
The Robert O. Paxton Papers include: arranged correspondence featuring exchanges between Paxton and his occasional collaborator and one-time coauthor Michael Marrus; research materials and notes for Vichy France and the Jews (published 1981); and course materials (including lecture notes, syllabi, and exams) for two history courses Paxton taught at Columbia from 1968 to 1995. The lecture notes--which help to illuminate Paxton's teaching style, the depth of his lecture preparations, and the evolution of his topical emphases across the decades--may be of particular interest to history and pedagogy scholars alike.
The collection also features extensive photocopied and original clippings on the French presidential election of 1981; clippings of French reviews for La France de Vichy (published 1972); and seventeen severely embrittled books covering legislative and parliamentary election results in France before World War II. All books are in French; publication dates range from 1911 to 1936.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 5 series:
Series I: Arranged Correcpondence
Series II: Research for Vichy France and The Jews
Series III: Course Materials
Series IV: Research
Series V: Printed Material
Subjects
Marrus, Michael Robert.; France--History--German occupation, 1940-1945.; Vichy (France); Jews, French.; Elections--France--1981.; Elections--France--1930s.; Correspondence; Lecture notes; Syllabi; Examinations; Historians
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Acquisition
Gift of Robert O. Paxton 1998 & 2004.
- Series I: Arranged Correcpondence
  - Letters between Robert O. Paxton and Michael R. Marrus; to Paxton from Roger Errera; and between Marrus and Errera, with enclosed photocopies. All concern research, drafts, and revisions of Vichy France and the Jews (pub. 1981)., New York; Oxford, England; Paris., 1979-1980, (15 t.l.s. ) (Box 1)
- Series II: Research for Vichy France and The Jews
  - Photocopies, handwritten notecards., 1980, (35 items ) (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of French-language periodicals and books, (15 items ) (Box 1)
  - Photocopies, typescripts in English and French., (24 items ) (Box 1)
  - Photocopies, handwritten notecards., 1980, (45 items ) (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of Le Monde and Le Monde juif articles., (10 items (multiple pages per item) ) (Box 1)
  - Statistical data on "Denaturalisations, 1940-44," and "Sequestres, 1940"., (40 Handwritten notecards (photocopies) ) (Box 1)
  - Photocopies of 1942 and 1943 data on "Administrateurs Provisoires", (2 items ) (Box 1)
- Series III: Course Materials
  - History of France Since 1848 (Hist. W3154
    Regarding Folders 9 through 19: According to Paxton’s notations, many lectures for this course were revised and reused in successive semesters. Wherever possible, they’ve been filed according to the most recent date noted. [As a result, Folder 19 (Spring 1995 Materials) below features many lectures that were originally drafted much earlier.] This arrangement affords some insight into Paxton’s revision process. However, to get a sense of the complete lecture run, researchers will want to examine the materials from different semesters/terms across the decades. Many lectures are undated and appear to be missing pages.
    - Miscellaneous typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from courses taught ca. 1963-1969. New York, NY, ca. 1963-1969, (30 items) (Box 2)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from Fall 1972 semester., New York, NY, 1972, (20 items) (Box 2)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from Fall 1975 semester., New York, NY, 1975, (25 items ) (Box 2)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from Fall 1978 semester., New York, NY, 1978, (20 items ) (Box 2)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from Spring 1981 semester., New York, NY, 1981, (6 items ) (Box 2)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from Spring 1984 semester., New York, NY, 1984, (20 items ) (Box 2)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from Fall 1985 semester., New York, NY, 1985, (50 items ) (Box 2)
    - Typewritten notes and research for lecture on French pluralism, Fall 1987 semester., New York, NY, 1987, (4 items ) (Box 2)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from Fall 1988 semester., New York, NY, 1988, (50 items ) (Box 2)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from Spring 1991 semester., New York, NY, 1991, (50 items ) (Box 2)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from Spring 1995 semester., New York, NY, 1995, (75 items ) (Box 2)
  - The European Lefts Since 1830 Parts I and II (Hist W4157x and W4157y)
    Regarding Folders 20 through 29: According to Paxton’s notations, many lectures for this course were revised and reused in successive semesters. Wherever possible, they’ve been filed according to the most recent date noted. [As a result, Folders 25-27 (Spring 1985 Materials) below feature many lectures that were originally drafted much earlier.] This arrangement affords some insight into Paxton’s revision process. However, to get a sense of the complete lecture run, researchers will want to examine the materials from different semesters/terms across the decades. Many lectures are undated and appear to be missing pages.
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from Fall 1970 and Spring 1971semesters., New York, NY, 1970-1971, (30 items ) (Box 3)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from 1973., New York, NY, 1973, (50 items ) (Box 3)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from 1973 (cont'd)., New York, NY, 1973, (50 items ) (Box 3)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from 1980., New York, NY, 1980, (25 items ) (Box 3)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from 1980 (cont'd)., New York, NY, 1980, (30 items ) (Box 3)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from 1985., New York, NY, 1985, (30 items ) (Box 3)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from 1985 (cont'd)., New York, NY, 1985, (40 items ) (Box 3)
    - Typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from 1985 (cont'd)., New York, NY, 1985, (30 items ) (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous typed and handwritten lectures, notes, handouts, syllabi, assignments, and exams from courses taught ca. 1970-1985. New York, NY, ca. 1970-1985, (40 items ) (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous materials (chiefly syllabi) for history courses taught by other professors, including David Crew and Michael Hanagan., New York, NY, ca. 1976-1979, (30 items ) (Box 3)
  - European Politics and Society Since 1919 (History 3206y), 1986-1998, (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Introduction to the Literature of European History (G8265x), 1997-1998 (Box 7)
- Series IV: Research
  Regarding the 1981 French Presidential Election
  - Promotional materials re. Francois Mitterand and the Socialist Party platform; photocopies of Le Monde and Economist articles; May 1981 issue of Le Nouvel Observateur., 1981-1982, (10 items ) (Box 4)
  - Printed, softbound Le Monde supplement, "Les Elections Legislatives de Juin 1981"; photocopies of Le Monde articles, 1981, 1981, (20 items ) (Box 4)
  - Photocopies of Le Monde articles., 1981, (50 items ) (Box 4)
  - Photocopies of Le Monde articles., 1981, (50 items ) (Box 4)
- Series V: Printed Material
  - Subseries V.1: Clippings
    - Clippings from French-language periodicals--reviews of La France de Vichy (pub. 1972). 1972-73, (30 items ) (Box 4)
    - French-language periodicals--reviews of La France de Vichy, 1972-73, (40 clippings ) (Box 4)
  - Subseries V.2: Books
    - Normand, Gilles Tout le Parlement: Biographies Sommaires des Senateurs et Deputes Francais au 15 Octobre 1924., Paris: Perrin & Co, 1925, (383 pages ) (Box 5)
    - Le Chartier, E. Bureaux de L'Avenir Economique. La France et son Parlement: Annuaire des Electeurs et des Parlementaires; edition de 1912., Paris, 1911, (1,358 pages ) (Box 5)
    - LaChapelle, Georges Le Temps. Elections Legislatives: 26 Avril & Mai 1936, Resultats Officiels., Paris, 1936, (338 pages ) (Box 5)
    - Corcos, Fernand Editions Montaigne. Catechisme des Partis Politiques: Historique, Doctrine et Programme de Tous les Groupements Politiques en France, pour les Elections de 1928., Paris, 1927, (303 pages ) (Box 5)
    - LaChapelle, Georges Librarie Geroirges Roustan Elections Legislatives: 22-29 Avril 1928; Resultats Officiels, Paris, [1928], (331 pages ) (Box 5)
    - LaChapelle, Georges Le Temps. Elections Legislatives: 1er & 8 Mai 1932; Resultats Officiels., Paris, 1932, (364 pages ) (Box 6)
    - LaChapelle, Georges Georges Roustan. Elections Legislatives du 11 Mai 1924: Resultats Officiels suivis de l'application de la R. P. departmentale., Paris, 1924, (263 pages ) (Box 6)
    - Henri Manuel, Editeur d'Art Senat: Notices et Portraits, 1921., Paris, 1921, (320 pages ) (Box 6)
    - Georges Roustan. Elections Legislatives du 16 Novembre 1919: Resultats Officiels avec application de la R. P. departementale., Paris, 1920, (249 pages ) (Box 6)
    - Georges Roustan. Elections Legislatives du 11 Mai 1924: Resultats Officiels suivis de l'application de la R. P. departementale., Paris, 1924, (252 pages ) (Box 6)
    - Imprimerie de la Chambre des Deputes. Chambres des Deputes: 14e Legislature; Notices et Portraits, 1928., Paris, 1929, (629 pages ) (Box 6)
    - Imprimerie de la Chambre des Deputes. Liste par Ordre Alphabetique de Mm. les Membres des Deux Chambres avec l'Indication de Leurs Adresses., Paris, 1916, (42, [30] pages ) (Box 6)
    - Imprimerie du Senat Liste par Ordre Alphabetique de Mm. les Membres des Deux Chambres avec l'Indication de Leurs Adresses., Paris, 1919, (64 pages ) (Box 6)
    - Imprimerie de la Chambre des Deputes. Liste par Ordre Alphabetique de Mm. les Membres des Deux Chambres avec l'Indication de Leurs Adresses., Paris, 1922, (105 pages ) (Box 6)
    - Imprimerie du Senat Liste par Ordre Alphabetique de Mm. les Membres des Deux Chambres avec l'Indication de Leurs Adresses., Paris, 1929, (202 pages ) (Box 6)
    - Bourgin, Georges, avec Jean Carrere et Andre Geurin. Editions Rieder. Manuel des Partis Politiques en France., Paris, 1928, (297 pages ) (Box 6)
    - Mennevee, R. Documents Politiques Parlementaires et Financiers: Repertoire des Senateurs et Deputes Directeurs ou Administrateurs de Societes Financieres, Commerciales, Industrielles et Economiques; Edition 1925., Paris, 1925, (90 pages ) (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous looseleaf pages and leaves from two or more unidentifiable volumes; the pages feature government directories, portraits, and statistics. [Paris], (1,000 pages ) (Box 6)
    - Masters Essay-- "La reception en France des travaux de Stanley Hoffman et Robert O. Paxton" by Emily Katz, 2007 (Box 7)